The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Makkan Period,
by Imam Anwr Al-Awlaki;
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
We covered the story of the Islam of Demaad(ضماد), and Amr Bin Absaa(عمرو بن عبسه).
We move on to the story of Abu Dharr رضي الله عنه.
I'm going to mention to you the Imam Ahmad(امام احمد) version.
Abu Dharr رضي الله عنه stated that me, my brother and my mother left our land of Ghifaar(غفار),
because our people used to be disrespectful of the Ash'hur-Ul-Hurum(أشهرالحرم).
Al-Ash'hur Ul Hurum(الاشهرالحرم) are four months, in which the Arabs used to consider sacred
and this would give them a break from warfare.
So, they would not allow killing, war during those four months.
And it was a firm tradition among them that you do not break, the sanctity of these four months.
The people of Ghiffar(غفار) were different,
these were professional Raiders of caravans, they didn't care about Ash'hur-Ul-Hurum(أشهرالحرم) and all this stuff.
They were Bedouins, who were raid caravans, steal, kill, corrupt,
and they didn't follow any rules or customers.
These are the people of Ghiffar(غفار).
And they had a bad reputation in Arabia, I mean people in Arabia knew Ghiffar(غفار).
These people don't abide by the rules, violent.
Abu Dharr رضي الله عنه before Islam, he disagreed with this style of life.
So he, his brother and mother decided to leave Ghiffar(غفار), just go out.
So, they went and they visited an uncle of theirs, he used to be a member of a different tribe.
And they stayed with him and Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) says he was very generous and hospitable to us , very kind.
But his relatives were becoming jealous.
How come he's treating us so well.
So what they did, they went up to the uncle of Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) and they told him;
When you are absent, Unais, Abu Dharr(ابو ذر)'s  brother, he goes and visits your wife, and he's interested in her.
The Uncle, quite naively, he went to Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) and Unais(اٌنَيْسْ) and mentioned to them, what he heard.
He said: People are saying that Unais(اٌنَيْسْ) is interested in my wife.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) was very angry and upset, this was false.
He was very angry and he said: All of the good what you have done to us, you have cancelled it.
All of the hospitality, your kindness is gone, after this accusation of yours,
and immediately packed up and left.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: My uncle was quite sorry and regretful for what he done and he wrapped himself in a cloth and he was crying.
But Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: We were so angry and we just left.
And now they settled the place close to Makkah.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) says that my brother, Unais(اٌنَيْسْ), he went to do some business in Makkah.
And he met a man who claims to be a Prophet, he met Muhammadﷺ.
So, Unais(اٌنَيْسْ) came back and he said, I found the man who was preaching a new religion, worshipping Allah alone.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: And at that time, I have already worshipped Allah for three years,
and revoked all of the worshipping of idols, I renounced it.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), you see these people, their Fitrah(فطرة), guides them and tells them that this is wrong, this is false.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) says: I've been praying to Allah for three years.
So, Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) was asked, how would you praying to Allah, he said:
I would pray to whichever direction Allah would points me to,
and I would pray in whatever way Allah guide me to,
and I would pray at night until I fall asleep,
and only the sun would wake me up in the morning.
So, he would pray, he doesn't know how to pray, but he would pray to Allah سبحانه وتعالى, for three years.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) asked, his brother Unais(اٌنَيْسْ), he said:
what does he teach?
So, Unais(اٌنَيْسْ) mentioned some of the teachings of Islam that he learned from Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then he asked him, What are the people saying about him?
Unais(اٌنَيْسْ) said: They're claiming that he's a sorcerer, and magician, a liar, and he went down the list.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said:
مَا اَشْفَيْتَ غَلِيْلِيْ
You haven't satisfied my hunger.
I want to go and investigate the matter myself.
What the people say might not necessarily be right.
The media of Makkah, the CNN of the day, or the ABC or whatever you call it, had all of these labels that they would brand Rasool Allahﷺ with
but Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) did not have trust in what the people are saying, he would have to go and meet Rasool Allahﷺ
and hear it from the messenger himself.
And that is what the Muslim is required to do.
تَبَيَّنُوْا
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says; when you receive some information verify it, Tabayyanoo(تَبَيَّنُوْا).
And that's where our scholars learn the science of Hadith(حديث).
They would verify.
It's not just enough to hear a Hadith(حديث) narrated from someone.
The scholars used to say:
هَاتُوا رِجَالَكُمْ اَوْ سَمُّوْلَنَا رِجَالَكُمْ
Whenever they would hear a Hadith(حديث), they would say mention, the names of your men.
Where did you hear this from?
Tell us the names, we want to know who you got this information from?
We just don't follow any hearsay.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر), he said: I went into Makkah and I asked the first man I saw in front of me.
I told them Can you please guide me towards Muhammadﷺ.
He said that man immediately started calling the men is Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and they started pelting me with stones, rocks, whatever they could get their hands on, until I fell unconscious.
He said: By the time I woke up, I was like
نُصبْ اَحْمَرْ
Nusub(نصب) the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they used to have these stones
idols which, they would slaughter and sacrifice their animals over.
So, they would be soaked with blood.
That's the description Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) gave of himself like a red pole, soaked with blood from head to toe.
He said: So I went to the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم), I drank water and I washed the blood of my body.
And then I went next to the Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
In the narration of Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ), it says that he stayed there for 30 days,
not knowing where to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: I did not have any food for the entire period, except for drinking the water of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
Now, I think physicians can tell us that a person can survive by drinking water for quite a while.
So, maybe that's not such a surprise.
But the surprising thing is what comes next,
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said:
And I started picking up weight,
until I was getting folds on my stomach.
You know for them the Bedouins, they would have flat tummies, they were very fit.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: I was gaining weight and now the flesh on my stomach was folding.
You know when you sit down and the flesh on the stomach folds.!
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) states that he then saw two women,
making Tawaf(طواف) and they would touch Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله) on every turn.
What's the story of Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله)?
Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله) are a man and a woman, who were in love and they couldn't get married.
And they had an appointment, a date to meet next to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه),
and they intended to fornicate next to the house of Allah.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى turned them into stones, on the spot.
After the passage of sometime the Mushrikeen(مشركين) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), started worshipping them,
started worshipping these two stones, Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله).
To show you how, when you open the floodgates for Shaytaan(شيطان), you can't close it, he just throws you in dungeons of darkness,
can never get out of it, it's spiral, if you get in, you'll never come out, darkness over darkness, one veil after another.
Now, the story of idol worshipping actually started as erecting statues after righteous men die.
Shaytaan(شيطان) came to the people of Noah(نوح) and told them after the righteous men have passed away.
Why don't you erect statues of these righteous men?
So, that they would remind you about Allah.
He came to teach them good.
He said: They would remind you about Allah سبحانه وتعالى, so they did that.
And then after a few generations, he started telling them, worship them.
That's how the idol worshipping grew.
So, here you have Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله) been worshiped,
and these two women would make Tawaf(طواف) and they would touch Isaaf(إساف) and Naila(نائله) on every turn.
Now Abu Dharr(ابو ذر), he despised idol worshipping.
So, he threw out a comment.
He said: Why don't you make one of them have intercourse with the other?
Either the woman did not understand, what he said or they didn't believe what they heard.
They continued.
When Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) saw that his words, did not deter them.
He threw out and even cruder comment,
and I'm not gonna mention it.
Now the woman were sure of what they heard, they immediately just started running and screaming,
wailing down the streets of Makkah and who did they run into?
Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر)
Muhammadﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) are seeing these two women running in the streets, screaming.
What's wrong with you?
They said that heretic over there,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: What's the matter with him?
They said: He spoke a word that fills the mouth.
تَمْلَأ الفَهمْ
In other words something that is unspeakable, very bad words.
Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), they went to meet this man, Abu Dharr رضي الله عنه and they started the conversation.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked Abu Dharr(ابو ذر): Where are you from?
مِنْ اَيْنَ الرَّجُلْ، قَالَ اَنَا مِنْ غَفَّارْ
He said: I am from Ghifaar(غفار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ placed his hands on his forehead.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: Rasool Allah ﷺ was surprised and amazed
to see somebody from Ghifaar(غفار) coming to Makkah, in search of the truth, from Ghifaar(غفار)!
These people who raid caravans, the ones who do not follow any rules or any customs, and he is searching for the truth in Makkah
and the people of Makkah, the ones who are considered to be the religious authority of Arabia, are rejecting my message.
فَكَرِهَا اَنْ اِنْتَسَبْتُ اِلَى غِفَارْ
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: I felt that he might have disliked that I mentioned that I'm from Ghifaar(غفار).
So, I extended my hand to pull his hand from his forehead.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) slammed my hand and told me, put your hand down.
And then the conversation continued and Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) ended up embracing Islam.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abu Dharr(ابو ذر):
اُكْتُمْ اِيْمَانَكْ
Keep your Eeman(ايمان) secret.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر), he went out the next day rather than keeping his Eeman(ايمان) secret,
he went in front of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and said:
اَشْهَدُ الله اله الَّا الله وَ اَشْهَدُ اَنَّ محمد الرَّسُول الله
He doesn't care about the consequences.
He said: They gathered around me and they beat me up, so bad, I was gonna die.
Until, Al-Abbas Bin Abdul-Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) came in and said, Do you know where this man is from?
Just one question,
he is from Ghifaar(غفار).
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) said: Immediately they just ran away.
All what you would see is them fleeing, running away from him.
But he did the same thing next day,
and he did the same thing third day,
and every day the same thing would happen they would come and beat him up,
until Al-Abbas(العباس) comes and tells this new group of people who are hitting him that the man is from Ghifaar(غفار).
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: And you know if this man gets killed by you, that none of your trade will make it safely to Syria.
They gonna take revenge of you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ then told Abu Dharr(ابو ذر), Go back to your people and convey the message to them.
And when you hear that I prevailed, come to me.
How long did Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) stay with Rasool Allah ﷺ.?
Quite a short time.
How much did he learn from him?
Probably not a lot.
Few verses, a few Ahadith(احاديث) here and there and that was it.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر), he went back to his people, Ghifaar(غفار).
And he started giving them Da'wah(دعوة),
slowly and slowly, people were accepting Islam, among the people of Ghifaar(غفار).
He said, by the time Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) almost half of my tribe were Muslim,
the whole tribe of Ghifaar(غفار).
He said, and then we decided to go and visit Rasool Allah ﷺ and the rest of the tribe have said,
when Rasool Allah ﷺ arrives and when we go and meet him, we will become Muslim.
So now, the whole tribe is Muslim.
All of them are Muslim,
the other half just said we're going to wait, it's a matter of time but then it will become Muslim and they did.
So one day when Rasool Allah ﷺ was in Madina, they see in the horizon, this dust cloud,
sign of an army approaching, large group of people.
So, some of the Sahabah(صحابه) have a rushed to their weapons thinking that maybe an army is approaching us.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
كُنْ اَبى ذر،
Be Abu Dharr(اَبُوْ زَرْ),
And the prophecy of Rasool Allah ﷺ was true.
It was Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) and all of his tribe of Ghifaar(غفار), coming to pledge their allegiance to Rasool Allah ﷺ, the entire tribe.
Now there was rivalry between two tribes Ghifaar(غفار) and Aslam(اسلم).
When Aslam(اسلم) heard that Ghifaar(غفار) became Muslim and they went and pledged allegiance to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
They immediately went to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said, we also want to become Muslim, two tribes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said,
غِفَارْ غَفَرُللهُ لَهَا ، وَاَسْلَمْ سَلَمَهُ اللهَ
Ghifaar(غفار), may Allah forgive them.
And Aslam(اسلم) may Allah, give them peace.
All of it started by the work of one man.
And how much did this man, know?
Was he a scholar at the time? No,
He just knew a few Ayaat(آيات), later on, Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) came to learn a lot.
But at that stage, he just spent a few days with Rasool Allah ﷺ and that was it
All of Ghifaar(غفار) became Muslim.
The last people in the desert that you would expect to accept Islam, they did become Muslim.
What can we learn from the story of Abu Dharr(ابو ذر)
Number one, again, the same lessons coming up.
وَالَّذِينَ اهْتَدَوْا زَادَهُمْ هُدًى
The ones, who search for guidance, Allah will give it to them.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) investigated the matter and Allah showed him the light, showed him the truth.
Number two, Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
بَلِّغُوا عنِّيْ وَلَوْ آيَةْ
Convey even one verse from me.
Whatever you have, convey it, share it, teach it, don't keep it to yourself.
Number three, courage.
Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) is an example of a person, who has courage, he wasn't intimidated by the fact that he's a foreigner in Makkah.
He stood and, he said: I'm a Muslim, and he was proud, and he paid for it dearly.
And then he went to his people, and he preached the message to them.
So, this shows you the courage of the personality of Abu Dharr(ابو ذر),
which is shown again and again and again, by the Sahabah of Rasool Allah ﷺ and this reveals to us the inherent qualities that they had.
And this is also one of the reasons why Allah سبحانه وتعالى chose them, to be the bearers of the message.
Because they had simplicity, and they had courage, and they had honesty,
and they had commitment to a cause when they believe in something they commit their lives to it.
Number four, verifying the truth,
Just because the people say that he is a sorcerer a liar, a magician, doesn't mean anything.
You have to go to the source and verify the information yourself.
Allah has given you a mind,
Allah has given you intelligence,
use it, don't just follow what the people are saying,
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that don't be an Imma'a(اِمَّعْ)
and when he was asked, What is the meaning of Imma'a(اِمَّعْ)?
He said; Whenever the people say, yes, you say, yes and wherever they say no, you say, no.
Don't just follow.
Number five,
لَا تَحقرَنَّ مِنَّ الْمعْرُوفِ شَيْئ ، وَلَوْ اَنْ تَلْقَى اَخَاك بِوَجْهِ الْحَسَنْ اَوْطَلقْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in this Hadith(حديث),
do not belittle any good deed.
Even if it is as small, as smiling in the face of your brother.
Don't belittle anything,
whatever good there is, don't consider it to be insignificant because everything good is significant.
And maybe that small thing, will make a difference on the Day of Judgment for you.
And it will be the criteria between Hellfire and paradise.
Maybe one small deed that you would do, which you don't pay any attention to, with tilt the scale to your side, for your favor.
And how do we deduct this lesson from the story of Abu Dharr(ابو ذر).
Abu Dharr رضي الله عنه he learned very little,
and all what he did was propagate the message.
And maybe he never expected that
this small effort of his would end up causing the whole tribe of Ghifaar(غفار) and the whole tribe of Aslam(اسلم) to become Muslim.
Maybe he only felt that he could convince a few group of people, maybe a few of his relatives.
But for this work, to end up bearing the fruits of two major tribes becoming Muslim,
may've Abu Dharr(ابو ذر) never thought about that.
But you throw the seed and Allah سبحانه وتعالى will make it grow.
And I'll mention to some contemporary examples about how sometimes you would do something very small,
and you will never pay attention to it, but it will make a big difference.
And there's a Hadith(حديث) by the way that says that
a person might speak a word that would please Allah and they don't pay attention to it,
but Allah سبحانه وتعالى will raise them up levels because of that.
And a person might speak a word that will anger Allah,
and because of that they will be thrown in hellfire.
It's a matter of a word, here or there.
There's a brother from Canada,
He said that he started having interest in learning religion at a very early age, around the age of nine.
He started studying religion, that's quite early.
He said, but he was turned away from Islam because of a lesson that he was taught in school about Islam.
He was shown some images that turned him away from Islam.
And then he said, he was going through some problems in his family
his father left, and his mother was on drugs.
So, he said, he completely forgot about this issue of religion, even though he had some early interest in it.
He said, and then he became a drug user and then he was promoted to being a drug dealer.
And he went to jail at the age of 14
So, he had a turbulent life
He said: Later on, towards my later teenage years.
After I came out of jail.
He said: I used to go to this park, in Canada, it's in the center of the city.
And that's where the drug addicts would usually congregate.
And we would all smoke and use our drugs and you'd find needles all over,
that's where we all come together and get high.
He said: So I went there, and I was sitting next to this guy who looked foreign,
and I was smoking my dope and I saw something interesting.
He said: The way that this guy next to me used to wrap is marijuana or hashish or whatever it was.
I am not very familiar with their specific terms.
He said: The way he used to wrap it, was different.
So, that caught my eye, I asked him, I see that the way you wrap your hashish or hash is different.
Where are you from? He said: I'm from Morocco.
He said: So you must be a Muslim. He said, Yes, I'm a Muslim.
He said: Can you tell me something about Islam?
Now he's remembering his early years of studying about religion.
He said: Tell me about Islam.
He said: So, this Moroccan guy was going through the tenants of Islam,
and we're all smoking, and we're very high and, I mean, he's speaking,
and I'm just receiving all of that information and absorbing it, and we were both high.
He is speaking very well and I'm understanding very well.
He said, for two hours continuously, we were talking about Islam.
He said, until we ran out of drugs we had nothing left.
He said and then we continued the conversation for another two hours, four hours in total.
And he said, that Allah سبحانه وتعالى sent another person to sit next to us.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) it was Qadar(قدر) of Allah,
an Algerian person, who wasn't on drugs or anything, he was just there, he happened to be there.
He said: He sent us to us, to correct whatever mistakes that, that person would make,
you know, people have different understanding of Islam, so they will correct each other.
And whenever one of them would mention, something wrong, the other person would correct the false information.
He said: We continued the conversation for four hours.
After that I became Muslim.
He said: Now, neither did the Algerian or Moroccan person know that I became Muslim
because I left and then became Muslim on my own.
And I stopped using drugs,
and I actually met him and he was during Da'wah(دعوة) at that time.
When he was telling us his story, there was a group of us.
So, one of the brothers who was sitting and hearing the story said a bad word about that Moroccan person, because of using drugs.
This Canadian Muslim brother his face turned red and he became very upset and angry.
And he said, Don't speak about him, because I became Muslim through him.
And every single thing that I do my Salah(صلاة), my Sayyam(صيام), my Zakaat(زكواة), my Zikr(زكر)
every single thing that I do, a copy of it will be deposited in his account.
Now, only Allah knows where that person is, he might still be in the park using drugs, he might be lost.
And he never knows that in his account, is Salah(صلاة) and Sayyam(صيام) and Zakaat(زكواة), they're all deposited, and he knows no idea about it.
He'll come on the day of judgment and see all of this and not know where it came from?
I was in those parks using drugs, where did all of these good deeds come from?
It all happened because of a few words that he said to a drug addict, like himself.
Now, maybe he never knew that this person would become Muslim, maybe he never intended it, he just was conversing, talking.
But he threw something good out there and these are the fruits of it.
So, never belittle anything,
maybe there's a small thing that you would do here and there.
And this would be the cause of your salvation on the Day of Judgment.
While the big things that you're doing, the big projects, the things that you're spending a lot of time on, wouldn't bear such an harvest.
And this is something that is in the hands of Allah.
So, you never know, therefore, you should do whatever good you can.
And leave it all there, just throw the seeds and Allah سبحانه وتعالى will make them grow.
But do not belittle anything.
وَلَوْ اَنْ تَلْقَا اَهَاك بِوَجْهِ الْحَسَنْ
Even if it is as much as smiling in the face of your brother.
We'll move on to the Hijrah(هجرة) to Abyssinia, the migrations.
Actually one more story that I was mentioned to you, to illustrate the same point further.
And this story was told to me by the person themselves, both stories were narrated to me by the persons themselves.
This was an African American,
who was a student at Berkeley University, University of Berkeley, University of California in Berkeley,
and he hear about Islam, but he didn't really know much about it.
African Americans tend to know about Islam, because they would have relatives who are Muslim,
or they would have a mosque next to them.
I mean, there's a very old tradition of Islam among African Americans in America.
So, you would usually find that they would have one member of their family or one friend who embraced Islam or is a Muslim.
So, in general, they are more familiar than anybody else in America, about Islam.
So, he knew about Islam but he didn't know the details about it, and he wasn't very interested in it.
He said: one day, in the beginning of the semester, I was walking through campus,
and a member of the Muslim Student Association was handing out copies of Qur'an, translations of Qur'an
He said: I picked up a copy, and on my way home on the bus, had nothing to do.
So, I opened up this book that was given to me as a gift, I had no idea what it is
And I opened up the first page, which is Al-Fatiha(ألفاتحه).
I saw that this is an introduction to the book and who reads introductions, so I flipped the page.
And I went straight to the body of the book.
Now the first thing that he would see next is, Surah Al-Baqarah(سورة البقرة)
He said: I began reading,
الم۝ ذَٰلِكَ الْكِتَابُ لَا رَيْبَ فِيهِ َ
There is no doubt in this book.
No doubts in this book.
He said, I was shocked by that statement.
Usually, when an author would write a book, they would start by apologizing for their mistakes, apologizing for their shortcomings.
And here you have an Author who was so confident about Himself, He stating that there's no doubt in My book,
and that's the first thing that you see in front of your eyes.
So, I was quite amazed and I wanted to know who is the author of this book?
I flipped the front cover didn't see any name, look at the back, didn't see any name.
I didn't know who wrote this book and I kept on reading.
And then eventually, I realized that this wasn't written by man, this comes straight from Allahعَزّ وجَلّ.
The power and the confidence that faces you as soon as you open the book,
he said: It made my heart shake.
And he said that was the reason, why I became Muslim Just that verse
There's no doubt in this book.
Now, again, that person who was giving out, Qur'an might be thinking, well, nobody's going to read this.
I'm just wasting my time, I'll just do it because they asked me to.
Because of that Qur'an this brother became Muslim.
And he's an Imam and he's very active in Da'wah(دعوة) and many people became Muslim through him,
and that was a product of a very small effort.
Alright We'll we move on to Al-Hijrah(الهجرة) to Al-Habasha(الحبشه).
There are two migrations that happened to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه).
The first one happened in the fifth year of Ba'atha(بعثه), following revelation.
And it was composed of a small group 12 men and four women.
The second Hijrah(هجرة), migration was a larger group and it was composed of 83 men and 18 or 19 women.
And this was more of a sporadic migration, maybe they didn't go in one, one group.
Now, how come there are two migrations to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه).
When the first group went to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه),
they heard a rumor that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) have became Muslim.
Rasool Allahﷺ received the Ayaat(آيات) of Surah Al-Najam(سورة النجم) and he recited those Ayaat(آيات)
and those Ayaat(آيات) were so powerful that it had so much effect on the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
when they heard the last Ayah(آية), which is an Ayah(آية) of Sujood(سجود),
Rasool Allahﷺ and the Muslims made Sujood(سجود), the Kuffar(كفار) made Sujood(سجود) with them.
They were so in tune with the Ayaat(آيات) they made Sujood(سجود) with the Muslims.
And this was the origin of that false rumor that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) became Muslim.
So, you had a group of the ones, who made Hijrah(هجرة) comeback to Makkah to find that it was a false rumor.
So now, we had another Hijrah(هجرة), which was a larger group.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he saw the pain and suffering that his companions are going through.
He said: Why don't you go to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه) because therein is a king, who does not oppress anyone.
لَا يُظْلَمْ عِنْدَه’ اَحَدْ
The king is just and he does not oppress anyone.
So, they went to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه) and the first to leave were Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) and his wife, the daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
There is a narration that says that Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) and his wife are the first to make Hijrah(هجرة) in the sake of Allah, after Loot(لوط).
They went to Al-Habasha(اَلْحَبَشَه) and the second group came in.
So they left Makkah.
Does that mean that the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) would leave them alone?
No.
even though, the Muslims in Abyssinia were no threat to Makkah politically.
They were no threat to the economical interests of Makkah.
Nevertheless, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) did not want to leave the Muslims alone.
In other words, even if we are left alone, we're not going to leave you alone.
We're going to stay after you until we destroy your religion.
So, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), assembled the delegation to go and meet with An-Najashi(النجاشي) to ask him to turn over the Muslims.
And who did they choose for this mission.?
Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص) and Abdullah Bin Rabiya(عبدالله بن ربيعة) in one narration and Amir Bin Rabiya(عامر بن ربيعة) in another narration,
but the central figure here is Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص).
Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص) was a diplomat, was a very intelligent man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
he had wide connections, he was a friend of the kings of the world at that time.
So, he was the right person to choose.
And he was a mastermind in plotting and planning.
And you can see that he was very good in conspiracies, against the Muslims.
That was the personality Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص) before Islam.
Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص), he went to An-Najashi(النجاشي)
and the plan was that he's going to go and meet the top officials first.
And he's going to give every one of them gifts, or in other words, bribes.
And he's gonna present to them his case and say that in your land, or some fools who ran away from Makkah,
we wanted to turn them over.
So, he wants to work it out with all of the top officials before he meets with An-Najashi(النجاشي).
So, when he talks to An-Najashi(النجاشي) and he consults his officials, they will all give him a unified opinion that you should have them over.
So, he went to everyone of them, he had a meeting with every one of them and gave them gifts.
And then he went to meet An-Najashi(النجاشي).
And he has told the officials that I prefer that you hand us over these people without having them meet An-Najashi(النجاشي).
I don't want them to meet An-Najashi(النجاشي), because their words are very effective.
They feared Qur'an.
So, he worked out the plan and he went to meet An-Najashi(النجاشي).
And he told An-Najashi(النجاشي), that there are some fools among us, who came to your land.
We know them and they left our religion, they didn't follow yours.
And they went on and on and on, and in the end, he said: We want you to hand them over to us.
Now all of the officials were already there and they said yes, hand them over.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) said: No
I will not hand over people who sought refuge in my land, until I hear their side of the story.
See the justice that An-Najashi(النجاشي) had.
And the choice of Rasool Allah ﷺ to have, his Sahabah(صحابه) go to the right place.
So, Najashi(النجاشي) called the Muslims to come and meet him.
The Muslims received the message, they were told that Amr Bin Aas(عمرو بن عاص) has met with An-Najashi(النجاشي)
and An-Najashi(النجاشي) wants to meet you.
So, they had the Shura'a(شورى), advice.
And Jafar Bin Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) was to be their spokesman the only spokesman and that they're going to speak the truth.
They went in to meet An-Najashi(النجاشي),
An-Najashi(النجاشي) asked them, what religion are you following?
You left the religion of your people, you didn't join my religion, you didn't join any of the religions of the world?
Who are you?
There's a Hadith(حديث) narrated by Umm Salamah رضي الله عنها,
it narrates this speech that Jafar Bin Abi Talib(جعفرإبن أبي طالب) gave in front of An-Najashi(النجاشي)
and I want to read the exact words of Jafar(جعفر) because there's a lot to learn from this presentation.
Jafar(جعفر) said, and Jafar(جعفر) is the cousin of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he is the brother of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
He said: O king! We were a people of polytheism.
We worshipped idols, ate the meat of animals that had died, offended rules of hospitality
and permitted things forbidden, as in the shedding of one another's blood, and so on.
We completely ignored matters of right and wrong
And so God sent to us a prophet.
So, notice the opening of the speech is talking about their background,
I want you to follow the speech and look at how Jafar Bin Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) arranged speech.
Keep in mind that he is talking to somebody who has no background whatsoever about Islam, he doesn't know anything about it.
He's speaking to someone who's Christian, and he's speaking to a king.
So, he gave him background information of who, we used to be, this was our situation.
"We were people of Shirk(شرك) who used to worship idols we used to eat the meat of dead animals.
We offended rules of hospitality and permitted things forbidden,
We used to shed each other's blood, we completely ignored matters of right and wrong.
So, he gave him an impression that we used to live in a chaotic stage.
And then, he said, And so God sent to us a prophet from among ourselves,
whose honesty and trustworthiness we knew well.
With this statement, he has established credibility in the Prophet.
So now, An-Najashi(النجاشي) knows that Muhammadﷺ is from among the people,
his people know him very well, they know his trustworthiness, and they know his truth.
He summoned us to pray to God alone, and without associate told us to respect rights of kinship,
to honor rights of hospitality, to pray to God, the Almighty and glorious
to fast for Him and to worship none other than Him.
Here he gave him issues of Tauheed(توحيد), oneness of Allah, and also the morals that Islam teaches.
He gave him a little bit of both.
And he said: And he, and so he called us to God, to affirm His oneness to worship Him
and to tear down all the other stones and idols, we and our forefathers had worshipped apart from Him.
He ordered us to be truthful in our speech, to keep up to our trust, to respect kinship ties, and hospitality rights
and to abandon things forbidden and the shedding of blood.
He forbade us to do anything immoral to tell lies, to misuse the fund of orphans, or to make false accusations against women of virtue.
He ordered us to worship God, and to associate no other God with Him.
He told us to pray, to give alms and to fast.
And then he enumerated for him all aspects of Islam.
Can anyone have any disagreement with anything that Jafar(جعفر) said?
Truth, trustworthiness.
So, it's important when you're speaking to somebody who don't know anything about Islam,
to illuminate to them the aspects of Islam, the good teachings of Islam.
Sometimes in our Daw'ah(دعوة), we assume that people know that Islam teaches good, many don't and Jafar(جعفر) took that into consideration.
And he went through the morals and the character building that Islam promotes.
In addition to talking about the Ibadaat(عبادات) he spoke about Salah(صلاة), Zakaat(زكواة) and Sayyaam(صيام).
And he also spoke about the Tauheed(توحيد), which is very important to present,
the worship of Allah alone, and tearing down the stones and idols.
You can also notice that it was very brief and to the point,
he didn't go on and on and on in details, he didn't turn it into an argument or debate.
Because remember, he's dealing with the king
You can't argue with such a person if you want to bring them closer to Islam.
So, he made it a very short and brief presentation.
But it's complete, it's comprehensive, there's nothing missing.
And then he said: And so we believed in him and trusted him,
following him in the instructions he brought from God,
we worship God alone without partner and associating no one with Him.
We forbade what he has forbidden and considered permissible, what he allowed us.
But our people aggressed against us and harmed us
seeking to draw us out of our faith to return us to the worship of idols instead of God.
And to have us again, consider permissible the abominations we had previously allowed.
When they treated us with violence and persecution besieged us and prevented us from performing our religion.
We left for your country and chose you above others
we desire your hospitality and hoped, we would not be harmed in your domain, O King.
Wonderful ending!!
Let's look at the statements before that.
He said our people aggressed against us, harmed us.
They tried to force us to give up our faith.
They besieged us, they persecuted us.
Don't you think that this will this will strike a chord with An-Najashi(النجاشي),
who was coming from a Christian background
that stresses the issue of suffering and sacrifice.
So, these words must have brought An-Najashi(النجاشي) closer
and would throw in his heart feelings of mercy towards these people
and a feeling of something that we have common between us.
This suffering sounds like the suffering Eesa(عيسى) went through,
sounds similar to what the prophets went through.
Because this is a man who was steeped in his religion.
And then in the end, Jafar Bin Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) said:
the reason why we came here, is because we were looking forward to your hospitality
and we chose you over all other kings of the world.
An-Najashi(النجاشي), the Negus replied, Negus is the translation of An-Najashi(النجاشي).
He said, Did you bring anything with you from what he brought.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) now wants to hear Qur'an.
Jafar Bin Abi Talib(جعفر إبن أبي طالب) recited some Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an.
Which Ayaat(آيات) did he choose.?
There's many Ayaat(آيات) that he could choose, which Ayaat(آيات) did he choose.?
Surah Maryam(سورة مريم)!
Look at the choice of Ayaat(آيات),
he recited to him verses from Surah(سورة) Maryam(مريم)
Umm Salamah(ام سلمه) says that, I swear, the Negus wept so hard, his beard was soaked.
And all his bishops cried so hard, they wet their Bibles.
So, it must have been an emotional presentation and recitation
to cause An-Najashi(النجاشي), the king and his bishops to cry.
An-Najashi(النجاشي) wetted his beard and the bishops wetted their Bibles, which were laying in front of them.
One brother, he was working as a taxi driver in the US.
He said: I was asked to drive a priest from Coronado Island to San Diego.
Coronado Island is an island outside of San Diego, in the US,
which was quite a long distance within the city.
And it was very late at night.
So, we had a conversation and he asked me,
What are you?
I said: I'm a Muslim.
Who are you? He said, I'm a Catholic priest.
And I'm here for a convention.
So, this brother said, Do you know that our Qur'an has spoken about Jesus?
Would you like me to recite to some verses in Qur'an about Jesus?
He said: Yes, go ahead.
So, the brother said: I went on reciting verses from Surah Maryam(سورة مريم) and translating them
and I kept on going on and on and on and the priest was silent, sitting in the back, it was late at night, and he was sitting in the back.
He said, then suddenly the priest tell me to stop this is my destination.
The brother said: When I looked at him, I saw tears running down his cheeks.
That is how strongly influenced he was by the verses of Surah Maryam(سورة المريم).
He said what the good thing after that he gave me a 100 Dollar tip.
So, people who love Eesa(عيسى), who love Jesus, when they hear the story of Jesus in Qur'an it's, it's quite emotional
So, it cause An-Najashi(النجاشي) to weep.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًاكَثِيْرَا